{
    "chapter_metadata": {
        "chapter_id": "10.English.06",
        "standard": "10",
        "subject": "History",
        "medium": "English",
        "chapter_name": "Entertainment and History"
    },
    "questions": [
        {
            "question_id": 1,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "What help refresh our minds and give a feeling of happiness?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Hard work",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Sources of entertainment",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Strict discipline",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Only reading",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Sources of entertainment"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 2,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Entertainment that anticipates an individual's mental-physical participation is called _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Passive entertainment",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Active entertainment",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Social entertainment",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Mass entertainment",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Active entertainment"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 3,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Watching a sports match or listening to music are examples of _______ entertainment.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Active",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Mental",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Passive",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Physical",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Passive"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 4,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Remains of clay dolls used as puppets have been found in _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Roman Empire",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Harappan civilisation",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "British period",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Modern Maharashtra",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Harappan civilisation"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 5,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The narrator in a Kathputali stage show is known as _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Haridas",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Sutradhara",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Kathekaribuva",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Art Director",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Sutradhara"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 6,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Dashavatara shows are presented in which regions of Maharashtra?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Vidarbha",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Marathwada",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Konkan and Goa",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Khandesh",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Konkan and Goa"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 7,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Dashavatara stories are based on the 10 incarnations of _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Shiva",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Ganesha",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Vishnu",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Rama",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Vishnu"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 8,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Who is considered the pioneer of Marathi theatre?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Vishnudas Bhave",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Shyamji Naik Kale",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Acharya Atre",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Vijay Tendulkar",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Vishnudas Bhave"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 9,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The type of Bhajan where devotees move in circular fashion is called _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Songi Bhajan",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Khanjiri Bhajan",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Chakri Bhajan",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Classical Bhajan",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Chakri Bhajan"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 10,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Tukadoji Maharaj introduced which new form of Bhajan?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Chakri Bhajan",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Khanjiri Bhajan",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Songi Bhajan",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Rashtriya Keertan",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Khanjiri Bhajan"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 11,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Who is supposed to be the founder of the Keertana tradition?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Saint Namadev",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Saint Tukaram",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Naradmuni",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Saint Eknath",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Naradmuni"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 12,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Who is known as the first keertankar of Maharashtra?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Saint Eknath",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Saint Namadev",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Saint Gadge Maharaj",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Dattopant Patwardhan",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Saint Namadev"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 13,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The tradition of 'Rashtriya Keertan' was started by _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Mahatma Phule",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Saint Gadge Maharaj",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Dattopant Patwardhan",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Naradmuni",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Dattopant Patwardhan"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 14,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "A metaphorical song with spiritual and ethical lessons is called _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Lalit",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Bharud",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Powada",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Tamasha",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Bharud"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 15,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The word 'Tamasha' is of _______ origin.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Marathi",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Hindi",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Persian",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Sanskrit",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Persian"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 16,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The show of Tamasha begins by singing the praise of Lord Ganesha, known as _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Gavalan",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Vag",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Gana",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Aarati",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Gana"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 17,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "A dramatic narration by alternatingly reciting poetry and prosaic extracts is _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Bharud",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Keertan",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Powada",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Bhajan",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Powada"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 18,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The Powada narrating the killing of Afzal Khan was composed by _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Tulasidas",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Adnyandas",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Umaji Naik",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Vishnudas Bhave",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Adnyandas"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 19,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Who wrote the first printed script for the Marathi play 'Thorale Madhavrao Peshwe'?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Vishnudas Bhave",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "V.J. Kirtane",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Acharya Atre",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Annasaheb Kirloskar",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "V.J. Kirtane"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 20,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Annasaheb Kirloskar is famous for which popular musical play?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Sharada",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Ekach Pyala",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Sangeet Shakuntal",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Mooknayak",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Sangeet Shakuntal"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 21,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The metaphorical drama 'Keechakvadh' was written to denounce which government?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Mughal Government",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Peshwa Government",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "British Government",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Portuguese Government",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "British Government"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 22,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "In 'Keechakvadh', who represented the insolent Viceroy Lord Curzon?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Bheem",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Yudhishthira",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Keechaka",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Draupadi",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Keechaka"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 23,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Who wrote the play 'Natasamrat', styled after Shakespeare's 'King Lear'?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Vijay Tendulkar",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Vishnu Waman Shirwadkar",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Vasant Kanetkar",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Acharya Atre",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Vishnu Waman Shirwadkar"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 24,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The honor of making the first full length movie in India goes to which state?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "West Bengal",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Tamil Nadu",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Maharashtra",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Uttar Pradesh",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Maharashtra"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 25,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The movie 'Pundalik' released in 1912 was made with help from _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Dadasaheb Phalke",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Foreign technicians",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Local drama troupes",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "The British Army",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Foreign technicians"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 26,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Which movie was the first to be processed completely in India?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Pundalik",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Sairandhri",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Raja Harischandra",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Sant Tukaram",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Raja Harischandra"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 27,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Who is known as 'Mistri' in the history of Indian cinema?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Dadasaheb Torane",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Baburao Painter",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Anandrao Painter",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Bhalaji Pendharkar",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Baburao Painter"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 28,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Which historical movie was banned by the British government for spreading nationalistic sentiments?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Simhgarh",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Kalyancha Khajina",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Bajirao-Mastani",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Mughal-e-Azam",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Bajirao-Mastani"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 29,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Who was the first woman producer in the Indian film industry?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Kamalabai Mangarulkar",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Meena Kumari",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Draupadi",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Savitri",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Kamalabai Mangarulkar"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 30,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Which movie received international acclaim at a film festival in Paris?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Raja Harischandra",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Sant Tukaram",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Ramshastri",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Dhanya te Santaji Dhanaji",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Sant Tukaram"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 31,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The special division of the Government of India for making documentaries is _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Censor Board",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "National Archives",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Films division",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Asiatic Society",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Films division"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 32,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "In theatre, accuracy of stage backdrops requires knowledge of history of _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Sports",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Arts and architecture",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Science",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Linguistics",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Arts and architecture"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 33,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Materials like horns and ivory were used in ancient India to make _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Weapons",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Puppets",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Paintings",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Drums",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Puppets"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 34,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The invocation of Lord Ganesha at the beginning of a Dashavatara show is done by the _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Haridas",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Kathekaribuva",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Sutradhara",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Vag",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Sutradhara"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 35,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Which of these is a solo keertan tradition?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Varakri Keertan",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Haridasi Keertan",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Rashtriya Keertan",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Satyashodhak Keertan",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Haridasi Keertan"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 36,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The Poorvarang of Haridasi keertan ends with the _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Naman",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Nirupan",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Uttarrang",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Gavalan",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Nirupan"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 37,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Lalit belongs to which keertan tradition?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Varakri",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Haridasi",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Naradiya",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Rashtriya",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Naradiya"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 38,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Which saint's Bharuds are very popular in Maharashtra?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Saint Tukaram",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Saint Dnyaneshwar",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Saint Eknath",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Saint Namadev",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Saint Eknath"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 39,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Traditional Tamasha type focusing on dance and music is _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Dholakicha Phad",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Sangeet Bari",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Vag",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Powada",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Sangeet Bari"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 40,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The second part of a Tamasha show presents the _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Gana",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Gavalan",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Vag",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Bharud",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Vag"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 41,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "A troupe of Dashavatara artists is called a _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Vag",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Sangeet Bari",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Phad",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Mandali",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Phad"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 42,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Balkrishnbuva Ichalkaranjikar introduced which music to Maharashtra?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Carnatic music",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Folk music",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Classical khyal music",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Sufi music",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Classical khyal music"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 43,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Which play comments on the evil custom of marrying young girls to aged men?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Sangeet Shakuntal",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Sharada",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Ekach Pyala",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Mooknayak",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Sharada"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 44,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The era of silent movies began with the technology of _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Sound recording",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Motion pictures",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Television",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Puppetry",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Motion pictures"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 45,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Dadasaheb Phalke's first movie was released in _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "1910",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "1912",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "1913",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "1918",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "1913"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 46,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "The movie 'Savakari Pash' by Baburao Painter was based on _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Mythology",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Historical theme",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Realistic social issue",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Army life",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Realistic social issue"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 47,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Which actor performed the role of Saint Tukaram in the acclaimed film?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Dadasaheb Phalke",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Roshan Seth",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Vishnupant Pagnis",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Baburao Painter",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Vishnupant Pagnis"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 48,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "To write movie dialogues, knowledge of the culture and _______ of the concerned period is necessary.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Science",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Geography",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Language",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Sport",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Language"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 49,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Keertan is traditionally performed in a _______.",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Cinema hall",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Temple",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "School ground",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Market",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Temple"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 50,
            "question_type": "MCQ",
            "question": "Which of these is an example of active entertainment?",
            "options": [
                {
                    "option_id": 1,
                    "text": "Listening to music",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 2,
                    "text": "Watching a movie",
                    "is_correct": false
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 3,
                    "text": "Practicing of handicrafts",
                    "is_correct": true
                },
                {
                    "option_id": 4,
                    "text": "Watching sports",
                    "is_correct": false
                }
            ],
            "answer": "Practicing of handicrafts"
        },
        {
            "question_id": 51,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What are the sources of entertainment?",
            "answer": "Various hobbies, games, drama, films, writing, and reading are the primary sources of entertainment that help refresh our minds."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 52,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Why is healthy entertainment essential?",
            "answer": "Excellent quality entertainment is essential for the healthy growth of one’s personality, keeping the mind lively and making one feel physically energetic."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 53,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Define active entertainment.",
            "answer": "Active entertainment anticipates an individual’s mental and physical participation, such as practicing handicrafts or participating in sports."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 54,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is passive entertainment?",
            "answer": "Passive entertainment is where an individual is not an actual participant but only a viewer, like watching a movie or listening to music."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 55,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Mention materials used to make puppets in ancient India.",
            "answer": "In ancient India, materials like wood, wool, leather, horns, and ivory were commonly used to make puppets for traditional shows."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 56,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Describe the Kathputali tradition of puppetry.",
            "answer": "Kathputali is a traditional Indian puppetry art with two styles, developed in Rajasthan and southern regions, involving shadow, hand, and string puppets."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 57,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the role of the 'Sutradhara' in puppetry?",
            "answer": "The Sutradhara is the narrator whose role is crucial to the success of the Kathputali stage show, explaining the story to the audience."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 58,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "When are Dashavatara shows usually presented?",
            "answer": "Dashavatara shows are part of the folk theatre in Maharashtra and are typically presented in Konkan and Goa after the harvesting season is over."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 59,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "List the 10 incarnations of Vishnu depicted in Dashavatara.",
            "answer": "The incarnations are Matsya, Koorma, Varaha, Narsimha, Wamana, Parashurama, Ram, Krishna, Buddha, and Kalki."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 60,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "How do Dashavatara shows conclude?",
            "answer": "The shows end with the breaking of a 'dahihandi' (pot of curds), followed by an aarati and singing praises of the God."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 61,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Define 'Bhajan'.",
            "answer": "Bhajan is the tradition of singing songs in praise of God and chanting God’s name, accompanied by instruments like taal, mridangam, or pakhavaj."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 62,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is 'Chakri Bhajan'?",
            "answer": "In Chakri Bhajan, devotees keep moving in a circular fashion and sing devotional songs without any break."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 63,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Explain 'Songi Bhajan'.",
            "answer": "In Songi Bhajan, singer-actors act as devotees and deliver dialogues through devotional songs while performing."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 64,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who introduced momentum to the Bhakti movement in Gujarat?",
            "answer": "Saint Narasi Mehta gave momentum to the Bhakti movement in Gujarat through his devotional compositions."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 65,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is 'Keertan'?",
            "answer": "Keertan is a traditional form of devotional performance involving oratory, singing, dance, and humour, usually performed in temples."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 66,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What are the two main traditions of keertan in Maharashtra?",
            "answer": "The two main traditions are Naraadiya (or Haridasi), which is a solo performance, and the Varakari tradition, which emphasizes collective participation."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 67,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Explain 'Poorvarang' and 'Uttarrang' in Haridasi keertan.",
            "answer": "Poorvarang involves praising God and explaining a main theme, while Uttarrang consists of narrating a story to illustrate that theme."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 68,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is 'Rashtriya Keertan'?",
            "answer": "Developed during the independence movement, Rashtriya Keertan creates awareness by narrating life stories of great leaders and social reformers."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 69,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who started the tradition of Rashtriya Keertan?",
            "answer": "The tradition of Rashtriya Keertan was started by Dattopant Patwardhan of Wai in Maharashtra."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 70,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What issues did Saint Gadge Maharaj focus on in his keertans?",
            "answer": "Saint Gadge Maharaj focused on social issues like the abolition of caste, cleanliness, and deaddiction in his keertans."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 71,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is 'Lalit'?",
            "answer": "Lalit is an old theatrical form of entertainment in Maharashtra belonging to the Naradiya Keertan tradition, popular in Goa and Konkan."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 72,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "How are Bharuds helpful in education?",
            "answer": "Saint Eknath composed Bharuds with the specific purpose of educating people on various ethical and spiritual aspects of life through humour and rhythm."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 73,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Define 'Tamasha'.",
            "answer": "Tamasha is a Persian word meaning 'pleasing sight', which developed into an independent art form in the 18th century combining folk and classical traits."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 74,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Distinguish between Sangeet Bari and Dholakicha Phad in Tamasha.",
            "answer": "Sangeet Bari emphasizes dance and music over drama, whereas Tamasha with 'Vag' (drama) as the main part is called Dholakicha Phad."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 75,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is 'Vag' in Tamasha?",
            "answer": "Vag is the dramatic part of a Tamasha show that became lively and entertaining through spontaneous humour."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 76,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is a 'Powada'?",
            "answer": "Powada is a dramatic ballad narrating the great deeds of heroic men and women by alternatingly reciting poetry and prosaic extracts."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 77,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Mention two well-known examples of Powada from Chhatrapati Shivaji's time.",
            "answer": "Adnyandas's Powada on the killing of Afzal Khan and Tulasidas's Powada on the battle of Sinhagad are famous examples."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 78,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "How were Powadas used during the 'Samyukt Maharashtra' movement?",
            "answer": "During the 'Samyukt Maharashtra' movement, Powadas were used as a powerful medium for creating public awareness among the people."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 79,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What are the essential factors of theatre?",
            "answer": "Theatre comprises factors like script, director, artists, make-up, costumes, stage, lighting arrangement, audience, and critics."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 80,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who were the patrons of drama in Tanjore?",
            "answer": "The rulers of the Bhosale family of Tanjore were great patrons of drama, writing and translating several Sanskrit plays."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 81,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Which was the first play presented by Vishnudas Bhave?",
            "answer": "'Seetaswayamvar' was the first mythological play presented by Vishnudas Bhave, the father of Marathi theatre."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 82,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What were 'farcical plays' in Marathi theatre?",
            "answer": "Farcical plays were humorous stage plays that dealt with various social issues in a light-hearted way to entertain and educate."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 83,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What change did V.J. Kirtane bring to Marathi theatre?",
            "answer": "V.J. Kirtane wrote the first complete script for a play in 1861, ending the tradition of spontaneous dialogues."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 84,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "How did classical music influence Marathi theatre?",
            "answer": "The growing popularity of classical khyal music in the 19th century led to the origin and huge popularity of musical Marathi theatre."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 85,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the theme of the musical play 'Sharada'?",
            "answer": "Govind Ballal Deval's 'Sharada' comments on the social evil of marrying very young girls to aged men using a humorous style."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 86,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Explain the metaphorical drama 'Keechakvadh'.",
            "answer": "K.P. Khadilkar’s 'Keechakvadh' used Mahabharata characters to metaphorically denounce the insolent attitude of the British government under Lord Curzon."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 87,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "List some popular 20th-century historical Marathi plays.",
            "answer": "Popular plays include 'Raygadala Jevha Jag Yete', 'Ghashiram Kotwal', and 'Tilak Ani Agarkar', which attracted large audiences."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 88,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who is Balgandharva?",
            "answer": "Narayanrao Rajahamsa, popularly known as Balgandharva, was a legendary Marathi stage artist remembered for his great acting and singing."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 89,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Name some early closed theatres built by the British in Mumbai.",
            "answer": "The British built closed theatres like Play House, Rippon, and Victoria in Mumbai to stage theatrical shows."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 90,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Define 'Cinema'.",
            "answer": "Cinema is a modern mass medium that brings together art and technology, originating with motion picture technology and evolving into sound movies."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 91,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "List some types of movies mentioned in the text.",
            "answer": "Types include satirical movies, documentaries, advertising films, children's films, movies about the army, and educational films."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 92,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What are 'Savedada's' contributions to Indian cinema?",
            "answer": "Harishchandra Sakharam Bhatvadekar (Savedada) was an important figure in the early development of Indian movies along with families like the Pitale family."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 93,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Mention silent movies created by Dadasaheb Phalke.",
            "answer": "Dadasaheb Phalke created silent movies like 'Mohini-Bhasmasur', 'Savitri-Satyavana', and documentaries on pilgrim centres like Nashik."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 94,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who was Baburao Painter?",
            "answer": "Baburao Painter (Mistri) was a pioneer filmmaker who made 'Sairandhri' and the first historical silent movie 'Simhgarh'."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 95,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Mention some historical Hindi movies of the pre-independence period.",
            "answer": "Historical Hindi movies from that era include 'Sikandar', 'Tansen', 'Samrat Chandragupta', and 'Mughal-e-Azam'."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 96,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Name some movies based on the Indian struggle for independence.",
            "answer": "Movies like 'Andolan' and 'Zansi ki Rani' deserve special mention for depicting the struggle for independence on screen."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 97,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "List production studios that played a role in the Indian film industry.",
            "answer": "'Bombay Talkies', 'Rajkamal Productions', 'R.K. Studios', and 'Navketan' played significant roles in developing the industry."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 98,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Why do art directors need knowledge of history?",
            "answer": "Art directors need historical knowledge to create accurate backdrops, costumes, jewellery, and hairstyles suitable to the theme's period."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 99,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the purpose of the 'Films division'?",
            "answer": "The Films division makes documentaries aimed at creating public awareness about various social and national issues."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 100,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Mention a movie based on the life of Mahatma Phule.",
            "answer": "Acharya Atre made a movie based on the life of Mahatma Phule in the post-independence period."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 101,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the difference between active and passive entertainment?",
            "answer": "Active entertainment requires an individual's mental or physical participation, like playing sports. Passive entertainment involves being a viewer or listener, like watching a movie or listening to music."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 102,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Describe the traditional Indian puppetry known as Kathputali.",
            "answer": "Kathputali is a traditional art with styles in Rajasthan and South India. It uses shadow, hand, wooden, and string puppets made from wood, wool, leather, or ivory."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 103,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the role of the Sutradhara in a puppet show?",
            "answer": "The Sutradhara is the narrator who explains the story on stage. The success of a puppet show depends significantly on the Sutradhara's skills."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 104,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is Dashavatara in Marathi folk theatre?",
            "answer": "Dashavatara is a folk theatre form in Konkan and Goa based on the 10 incarnations of Lord Vishnu. It is performed after the harvesting season."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 105,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "How are the actors in Dashavatara traditionally made up?",
            "answer": "Actors wear wooden masks to represent various characters. Only the characters of gods and demons wear these masks, and the show concludes with a dahihandi."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 106,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the origin of the word 'Tamasha'?",
            "answer": "The word 'Tamasha' is of Persian origin and it means a 'pleasing sight'. It developed as an independent art form in the 18th century."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 107,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Explain the two types of Tamasha.",
            "answer": "The two types are Sangeet Bari, which focuses primarily on dance and music, and Dholakicha Phad, where 'Vag' (drama) is the main part of the performance."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 108,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is 'Vag' in the context of Tamasha?",
            "answer": "Vag is the dramatic play performed in a Tamasha show. It is the main part of the Dholakicha Phad tradition and is often very lively and humorous."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 109,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Define 'Bharud' and its purpose.",
            "answer": "Bharud is a metaphorical song with spiritual and ethical lessons. Saint Eknath used it to educate people through humor and rhythmic music."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 110,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is a Powada?",
            "answer": "A Powada is a dramatic ballad that narrates the heroic deeds of men and women. It uses a mix of poetry and prosaic extracts for narration."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 111,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who is the 'Father of Marathi Theatre'?",
            "answer": "Vishnudas Bhave is known as the father of Marathi theatre. He presented the first mythological play 'Seetaswayamvar' in 1843."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 112,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What was the significance of 'Thorale Madhavrao Peshwe' in Marathi drama?",
            "answer": "Written by V.J. Kirtane in 1861, it was the first Marathi play with a completely printed script, breaking the tradition of spontaneous dialogues."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 113,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Explain the concept of 'Rasas' in performing arts.",
            "answer": "According to 'Natyashastra', there are nine fundamental moods or 'Rasas' like Shringar (love), Hasya (humour), and Veer (heroism) that are essential to performance."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 114,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is 'Sangeet Natak'?",
            "answer": "Sangeet Natak is a musical play tradition in Maharashtra. It became very popular with the rise of classical khyal music in the 19th century."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 115,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Why was the play 'Keechakvadh' famous during the British period?",
            "answer": "It was a metaphorical drama where the villain Keechaka represented the British Viceroy Lord Curzon, used to denounce the British government."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 116,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who wrote the play 'Sharada' and what was its theme?",
            "answer": "Govind Ballal Deval wrote 'Sharada'. It critiqued the social evil of marrying young girls to aged men in a humorous style."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 117,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the importance of 'Balgandharva' in Marathi theatre?",
            "answer": "Narayanrao Rajahamsa, known as Balgandharva, was a legendary actor and singer whose performances in musical plays are considered unparalleled."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 118,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "List some modern Marathi plays that gained popularity.",
            "answer": "Modern popular plays include 'Natasamrat' by V.V. Shirwadkar, 'Ghashiram Kotwal' by Vijay Tendulkar, and 'Tilak Ani Agarkar' by Vishram Bedekar."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 119,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the 'Films Division' of India?",
            "answer": "It is a government division that makes documentaries to create public awareness about social issues and national progress."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 120,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Name the first full-length Indian movie and its director.",
            "answer": "The first full-length movie was 'Raja Harischandra', released in 1913, and it was directed by Dadasaheb Phalke."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 121,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who was Baburao Painter?",
            "answer": "Baburao Painter (Mistri) was a pioneer filmmaker who made the first historical silent movie 'Simhgarh' and founded the Maharashtra Film Company."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 122,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Mention the significance of the movie 'Sant Tukaram'.",
            "answer": "Released in 1936, it was the first Indian movie to receive international acclaim at the Paris film festival."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 123,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What role does history play in the film industry?",
            "answer": "History is essential for maintaining accuracy in sets, costumes, and language in historical movies and documentaries."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 124,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who was the first woman producer in Indian cinema?",
            "answer": "Kamalabai Mangarulkar was the first woman producer, known for making movies in Marathi and Hindi like 'Savla Tanda'."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 125,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What are 'Keertana' performances?",
            "answer": "Keertana is a devotional performance involving singing, instrumental music, oratory, and humor to spread religious and social messages."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 126,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Distinguish between Haridasi and Varakari Keertan.",
            "answer": "Haridasi is a solo performance with 'Poorvarang' and 'Uttarrang'. Varakari keertan involves collective participation and is centered around the Varakari sect."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 127,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the focus of Rashtriya Keertan?",
            "answer": "Rashtriya Keertan focuses on creating national awareness by narrating stories of great leaders, social reformers, and Indian independence fighters."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 128,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Describe 'Lalit' as an entertainment form.",
            "answer": "Lalit is an old theatrical form in Maharashtra where actors represent various characters on stage, often performed as part of religious festivals."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 129,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is 'Bhajan'?",
            "answer": "Bhajan is the tradition of singing devotional songs in praise of God, accompanied by instruments like Taal and Mridangam."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 130,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who popularized 'Khanjiri Bhajan'?",
            "answer": "Khanjiri Bhajan was introduced and popularized by Rashtrasant Tukadoji Maharaj in Maharashtra."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 131,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Mention some materials used for making ancient dolls.",
            "answer": "Ancient dolls were made from clay, wood, ivory, and even materials like wool and leather for puppet shows."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 132,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "How did the Bhosale rulers of Tanjore contribute to drama?",
            "answer": "The Bhosale rulers were great patrons of art and wrote or translated several Sanskrit plays into regional languages."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 133,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What were 'Farcical plays'?",
            "answer": "Farcical plays were humorous dramas that used satire to comment on social issues and entertain the audience."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 134,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who wrote 'Thorale Madhavrao Peshwe'?",
            "answer": "V.J. Kirtane wrote 'Thorale Madhavrao Peshwe', which is a significant milestone as the first printed Marathi play script."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 135,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the theme of 'Ekach Pyala'?",
            "answer": "Written by Ram Ganesh Gadkari, 'Ekach Pyala' is a famous Marathi tragedy that highlights the destructive effects of alcoholism."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 136,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "How does 'Natasamrat' relate to Shakespeare?",
            "answer": "'Natasamrat', written by V.V. Shirwadkar (Kusumagraj), is a modern masterpiece styled after William Shakespeare’s play 'King Lear'."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 137,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Mention the first movie made with the help of foreign technicians.",
            "answer": "The movie 'Pundalik', released in 1912, was made in Mumbai with the help of foreign technicians."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 138,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the contribution of Anandrao Painter?",
            "answer": "Anandrao Painter was an early film enthusiast who constructed the first Indian movie camera and inspired Baburao Painter."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 139,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Who made the first historical silent movie in India?",
            "answer": "Baburao Painter made the first historical silent movie titled 'Simhgarh' in 1923."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 140,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "List some pre-independence historical Hindi movies.",
            "answer": "Notable movies include 'Sikandar', 'Tansen', 'Samrat Chandragupta', and 'Mughal-e-Azam'."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 141,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is 'Sangeet Shakuntal'?",
            "answer": "It is a famous musical play by Annasaheb Kirloskar that marks the beginning of the golden age of Marathi musical theatre."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 142,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Define 'Active Participation' in entertainment.",
            "answer": "Active participation means the individual is personally involved in the creative process, such as playing a game or making a handicraft."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 143,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the goal of children's movies?",
            "answer": "Children's movies are educational and entertaining films specially made to cater to the interests and psychology of children."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 144,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "How is 'Keertankar' defined?",
            "answer": "A Keertankar is a performer who conducts a Keertan, using oratory, singing, and storytelling to deliver religious and moral messages."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 145,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Name the director of the movie 'Ramshastri'.",
            "answer": "The movie 'Ramshastri' was directed by the Prabhat Film Company, known for its high-quality historical films."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 146,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is 'Sangeet Bari'?",
            "answer": "Sangeet Bari is a type of Tamasha that gives more importance to dance and music than to the dramatic play or 'Vag'."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 147,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Why were movies on independence struggle banned?",
            "answer": "The British government banned movies like 'Bajirao-Mastani' because they suspected they were used to spread nationalistic feelings against colonial rule."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 148,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "What is the significance of 1843 in Marathi theatre?",
            "answer": "In 1843, Vishnudas Bhave presented 'Seetaswayamvar', which is considered the first professional play in the history of Marathi theatre."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 149,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "How does history help an actor?",
            "answer": "Knowledge of history helps an actor understand the social context, language, and behavior of the character they are portraying."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 150,
            "question_type": "SHORT",
            "question": "Mention the role of 'Sutradhara' in Dashavatara.",
            "answer": "The Sutradhara in Dashavatara invokes Lord Ganesha at the beginning of the show and coordinates the entire performance."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 151,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the importance of entertainment in human life.",
            "answer": "Entertainment is essential for the healthy growth of one’s personality and refreshing the mind. It keeps our minds lively and fresh, which can also make us feel physically more energetic, eventually improving our efficiency at work. Pursuing hobbies and games helps in overall personality development. Since ancient times, festivals, sports, and performing arts have served this purpose. In the modern period, there are varied forms of active and passive entertainment available that help people manage stress and find happiness in daily life."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 152,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the tradition of Dashavatara theatre in Maharashtra.",
            "answer": "Dashavatara is a traditional folk theatre form popular in the Konkan and Goa regions of Maharashtra. It is based on the ten incarnations of Lord Vishnu, including Matsya, Varaha, and Krishna. The performance begins with an invocation of Lord Ganesha by the Sutradhara. Actors represent gods and demons using specific wooden masks and costumes. The shows are usually held after the harvesting season and are characterized by spontaneous dialogues and religious fervor. The show ends with the breaking of a dahihandi and an aarati to praise the deity."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 153,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Describe the evolution of Keertana in Maharashtra.",
            "answer": "Keertana is a devotional performance that originated in ancient times, with Naradmuni considered its founder. In Maharashtra, Saint Namadev is known as the first Keertankar. It involves two main traditions: the Naradiya (or Haridasi), which is a solo performance with a thematic 'Poorvarang' and narrative 'Uttarrang', and the Varakari tradition, which emphasizes group participation. During the freedom struggle, 'Rashtriya Keertan' emerged to create national awareness using the life stories of great leaders. Saints like Gadge Maharaj used Keertan to promote social reforms like cleanliness and the abolition of caste."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 154,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Write a detailed note on the Marathi Theatre tradition.",
            "answer": "Marathi theatre began in the 19th century with Vishnudas Bhave, who presented 'Seetaswayamvar' in 1843. Initially, plays were mythological and dialogues were spontaneous. In 1861, V.J. Kirtane wrote the first printed script for 'Thorale Madhavrao Peshwe'. The late 19th century saw the rise of musical plays or 'Sangeet Natak', made popular by Annasaheb Kirloskar and artists like Balgandharva. Theatre also addressed social issues, as seen in the play 'Sharada'. Metaphorical dramas like 'Keechakvadh' were used to protest against British rule. Modern Marathi theatre continues to thrive with diverse social and historical themes."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 155,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the development of the Indian Film Industry and Dadasaheb Phalke's role.",
            "answer": "The Indian film industry began with silent movies, with Dadasaheb Phalke playing a foundational role. He produced and directed India's first full-length movie 'Raja Harischandra' in 1913, processing it entirely in India. Phalke went on to create numerous silent movies and documentaries on pilgrim centers. His work paved the way for other pioneers like Baburao Painter, who made the first historical movie 'Simhgarh'. The industry transitioned to 'talkies' in the 1930s, and Pune's Prabhat Film Company became world-famous for its high-quality social and historical films. Today, the Indian film industry is one of the largest in the world."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 156,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "What are the professional opportunities for historians in the entertainment field?",
            "answer": "Historians have numerous professional opportunities in the entertainment industry. In theatre, they can work as consultants for set designers, ensuring the accuracy of stage backdrops and architecture. In the film industry, they are needed to verify the authenticity of costumes, weaponry, and language for historical themes. Historians can also work as scriptwriters, researchers, or technical advisors for documentaries and historical serials. Knowledge of history is also required to assess the value of art objects in the market and to contribute to digital journalism or web news portals focusing on historical content."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 157,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the significance of 'Tamasha' as a folk art form.",
            "answer": "Tamasha is a vibrant folk art of Maharashtra that developed in the 18th century. It combines elements of music, dance, and drama. There are two main types: Sangeet Bari, which is musical-centric, and Dholakicha Phad, which is drama-centric. A Tamasha show begins with 'Gana' (praising Lord Ganesha) and 'Gavalan', followed by the main dramatic play called 'Vag'. The 'Vag' is known for its witty dialogues and spontaneous humor. Tamasha serves as a powerful medium for entertainment and social commentary, reflecting the cultural identity of rural Maharashtra."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 158,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "How did Bharud and Lalit contribute to folk theatre in Maharashtra?",
            "answer": "Bharud and Lalit are old forms of theatrical entertainment that were used for spiritual and social education. Bharud, particularly those composed by Saint Eknath, uses humor and rhythmic music to deliver ethical lessons. Lalit, belonging to the Naradiya Keertan tradition, involves actors portraying various characters on stage during festivals. Both forms represent the early development of drama in Maharashtra. They helped bridge the gap between religious devotion and public entertainment, using folk narratives to reach the masses and instill moral values through engaging performances."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 159,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the role of historical movies in the pre-independence era.",
            "answer": "During the pre-independence era, historical movies were used as a subtle medium to inspire nationalistic feelings and criticize colonial rule. Filmmakers like Baburao Painter and Bhalaji Pendharkar made movies on historical themes, such as 'Simhgarh', which depicted the valor of Maratha warriors. Movies like 'Bajirao-Mastani' were sometimes banned by the British government because they were suspected of spreading anti-colonial sentiments. These films allowed the public to connect with their heroic past and fostered a sense of national identity. They played a significant role in the cultural resistance against the British through the emerging mass medium of cinema."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 160,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the evolution of 'Sangeet Natak' and its golden age.",
            "answer": "Sangeet Natak or Marathi musical theatre rose to prominence in the late 19th and early 20th centuries. It was heavily influenced by the growing popularity of classical khyal music. Annasaheb Kirloskar's 'Sangeet Shakuntal' is credited with starting this golden age. Legenday artists like Balgandharva performed in these plays, captivating audiences with their singing and acting. The plays were known for their elaborate music and were often based on mythological or social themes. This tradition made classical music accessible to the common people and remains a unique and highly respected part of Maharashtra’s cultural heritage."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 161,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Describe the various types of puppetry traditions in India.",
            "answer": "India has a rich tradition of puppetry dating back to ancient times, with remains of clay dolls found in Harappan sites. The Kathputali tradition has two distinct styles developed in Rajasthan and Southern India. It involves four main types: shadow puppets, hand puppets, wooden puppets, and string puppets. Puppeteers use materials like wool, leather, and wood to create detailed characters. The Sutradhara (narrator) coordinates the performance, telling stories from epics like Ramayana and Mahabharata. Puppetry serves as an important folk medium for storytelling and social education across various Indian states."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 162,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "What are 'Bharud' songs and how did Saint Eknath use them?",
            "answer": "Bharud is a metaphorical song form in Maharashtra that delivers spiritual and ethical messages through humor. Saint Eknath is the most famous composer of Bharuds. He designed them to be rhythmic and engaging, often incorporating everyday characters and social situations. The humor in Bharud made complex spiritual concepts easy for common people to understand. By using a popular folk format, Saint Eknath successfully used entertainment as a tool for social and moral education. Bharuds remain widely performed during pilgrimages and religious festivals today, continuing their legacy of mass education."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 163,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the contribution of the Prabhat Film Company to Indian cinema.",
            "answer": "The Prabhat Film Company, established in Kolhapur and later moved to Pune, was a leading production house in early Indian cinema. It was known for its high-quality technical standards and impactful social and historical movies. Famous films like 'Sant Tukaram', 'Kunku', and 'Ramshastri' were produced by Prabhat. 'Sant Tukaram' was particularly significant as the first Indian film to win an award at an international film festival in Paris. The company nurtured many talented actors, directors, and technicians, setting a high benchmark for the industry and influencing the future of Marathi and Hindi cinema."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 164,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "How did theatre in Maharashtra address social issues through plays?",
            "answer": "Theatre in Maharashtra has a long history of addressing and critiquing social issues. For example, the musical play 'Sharada' by Govind Ballal Deval used humor to denounce the practice of marrying young girls to older men. Ram Ganesh Gadkari’s 'Ekach Pyala' highlighted the tragic consequences of alcohol addiction. Metaphorical plays like 'Keechakvadh' were used to protest against the British government's policies. Modern plays like 'Ghashiram Kotwal' examined power dynamics and political corruption. By using the stage as a platform for social commentary, Marathi theatre has played a crucial role in social reform and public education."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 165,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the role of 'Powada' in the freedom struggle and social movements.",
            "answer": "Powada is a dramatic ballad tradition in Maharashtra that celebrates heroic deeds. During the British period, Powadas were used to narrate stories of warriors like Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj to inspire nationalistic pride. In the Indian independence movement, they became a powerful medium for creating public awareness and mobilizing the masses against colonial rule. Later, during the 'Samyukt Maharashtra' movement, Powadas were again used to unite people and express regional identity. Artists (Shahirs) use rhythmic singing and energetic performance to keep the audience engaged, making Powada an effective tool for social and political communication."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 166,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Describe the features of 'Lalit' and its regional popularity.",
            "answer": "Lalit is an old theatrical form of entertainment common in the Goa and Konkan regions of Maharashtra. It is considered an extension of the Naradiya Keertana tradition. In a Lalit performance, actors portray characters of various deities and mythological figures on stage. It is often performed as part of religious festivals like the annual festival of a village deity. The performance includes invocations, dramatic dialogues, and devotional music. Lalit represents a bridge between religious ritual and professional drama, and its regional popularity reflects the deep-rooted cultural and religious traditions of the coastal communities."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 167,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "How did the introduction of cinema change the landscape of entertainment in India?",
            "answer": "Cinema revolutionized entertainment in India by combining art and technology into a modern mass medium. It began with silent films by Dadasaheb Phalke, making mythology and history visible to large audiences. The arrival of sound in the 1930s allowed for musicals and social dramas, expanding its reach. Cinema surpassed theatre in popularity as it was more accessible and could use advanced visual effects. It created new career paths for actors, technicians, and historians. Today, Indian cinema is a global phenomenon, producing thousands of films in various languages and playing a central role in India’s social and cultural life."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 168,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the importance of 'accuracy' in historical serials and movies.",
            "answer": "Accuracy is vital in historical serials and movies to maintain credibility and respect for the past. Producers must ensure that the environment, architecture, and stage backdrops are correct for the period being depicted. Accuracy in outfits, jewelry, and weaponry is essential to create an authentic visual experience. Even the language and lingual expressions must reflect the concerned historical time. Historians are often hired as consultants to verify these details. Without this accuracy, the audience might receive a distorted view of history, which can affect the educational value and national identity associated with the story."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 169,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "What is the role of 'Sutradhara' in the Dashavatara performance?",
            "answer": "In Dashavatara, the Sutradhara is the central figure who coordinates the entire performance. He begins the show by invoking Lord Ganesha and explaining the theme to the audience. He often engages in witty banter with other characters, especially the 'Vidushaka' (clown), to keep the show lively. The Sutradhara is responsible for narrating the story and ensuring the smooth transition between different scenes. His role requires strong oratory skills and a deep understanding of the mythological stories. The overall success and rhythm of a Dashavatara performance depend heavily on the Sutradhara's leadership and skill."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 170,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the significance of the Bhakti movement in the development of 'Bhajan'.",
            "answer": "The Bhakti movement, which emphasized personal devotion to God, was the driving force behind the 'Bhajan' tradition. Saints across India used Bhajans to spread the message of equality and devotion. In Maharashtra, the Varakari sect popularized Bhajans as a form of collective worship. Different styles like 'Chakri Bhajan' and 'Songi Bhajan' developed to keep devotees engaged. In Gujarat, Saint Narasi Mehta gave momentum to the tradition, while Saint Tukadoji Maharaj introduced 'Khanjiri Bhajan' in modern times. Bhajans helped democratize religion by allowing people of all castes and classes to participate in singing praises of God together."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 171,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "How did the British influence the development of 'closed theatres' in India?",
            "answer": "Before the British period, drama was often performed in open spaces or temple courtyards. The British introduced the concept of 'closed theatres' to India, especially in cities like Mumbai. They built theaters like Play House, Rippon, and Victoria to host theatrical shows. These venues provided a controlled environment with better acoustics, lighting, and seating for the audience. The introduction of closed theaters encouraged the professionalization of Marathi theatre and led to more elaborate stage designs and backdrops. This shift changed the way plays were produced and consumed, laying the foundation for modern urban theatrical traditions."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 172,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the contribution of Baburao Painter to the technical side of Indian cinema.",
            "answer": "Baburao Painter, also known as 'Mistri', was a multi-talented pioneer who made significant technical contributions to early Indian cinema. He constructed his own movie camera and was an expert in art direction and set design. Painter was the first to use artificial lights for shooting, which allowed for better indoor cinematography. He founded the Maharashtra Film Company and made the first historical silent movie, 'Simhgarh'. His attention to detail in sets and costumes set new standards for authenticity. Painter’s innovative spirit and technical mastery influenced a generation of filmmakers and technicians, helping to modernize Indian film production."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 173,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "What is the 'Poorvarang' and 'Uttarrang' in the Keertana tradition?",
            "answer": "In the Haridasi or Naradiya Keertana tradition, the performance is divided into two parts. The first part, 'Poorvarang', consists of singing 'Naman' (praising God) and 'Nirupan', where the Keertankar explains a philosophical or religious theme using devotional songs. The second part, 'Uttarrang', involves narrating a mythological story or the life of a saint to illustrate and reinforce the theme explained in the Poorvarang. This structured approach allows the Keertankar to combine theoretical teaching with engaging storytelling, making the moral and religious messages more effective and memorable for the audience."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 174,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the significance of the play 'Natasamrat' in Marathi literature.",
            "answer": "'Natasamrat', written by the legendary poet V.V. Shirwadkar (Kusumagraj), is considered a milestone in Marathi theatrical literature. Styled after Shakespeare’s 'King Lear', it portrays the tragic downfall of a veteran stage actor who gives away his wealth to his children only to be neglected by them. The play is famous for its powerful monologues and deep exploration of human emotions and family relationships. It provides a grand role for actors, with several legendary artists delivering iconic performances. 'Natasamrat' remains highly popular and respected for its literary quality and its profound commentary on the nature of fame and old age."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 175,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "How did 'Vividh Bharati' change the reach of mass media in India?",
            "answer": "'Vividh Bharati', a service of All India Radio, significantly expanded the reach of mass media across India's linguistically diverse population. It broadcasts entertainment and informative programmes in 24 regional languages and 146 local dialects. This massive linguistic reach allowed the government to communicate schemes and policies even to remote rural areas. Vividh Bharati also played a major role in popularizing Indian film music and providing a platform for local art forms. By catering to various social groups like farmers and workers in their own dialects, it became a powerful tool for social awareness and national integration."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 176,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Describe the role of the 'Vidushaka' in folk theatre forms like Tamasha.",
            "answer": "The Vidushaka or clown is an essential character in Marathi folk theatre, especially in Tamasha and Dashavatara. His primary role is to provide comic relief through witty remarks, physical humor, and satire. In Tamasha, the Vidushaka often engages in a dialogue with the Sutradhara or the lead dancer, using humor to comment on current social and political situations. While he makes the audience laugh, his satire often contains deep social critiques. The Vidushaka acts as a bridge between the performers and the audience, keeping the performance engaging and relevant. His role requires great spontaneity and a quick wit."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 177,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the 'utilitarian' purpose of applied arts in the entertainment industry.",
            "answer": "Applied arts in the entertainment industry serve a 'utilitarian' purpose by combining artistic creativity with functional requirements. For example, in theatre and film, an art director creates sets that are not just beautiful but also functional for the actors and the camera. Costume designers create outfits that define a character while being wearable. Calligraphy and graphic design are used for posters and advertisements to attract audiences. This combination of beauty and utility makes these artistic creations economically viable and essential for the production process. Applied arts professionalize creativity, providing numerous career opportunities in set design, makeup, and advertising."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 178,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "How do documentaries made by the 'Films Division' help in public education?",
            "answer": "The Films Division of India produces documentaries aimed at educating the public on various social, national, and historical issues. These short films cover themes like health, cleanliness, national integration, and the lives of great personalities. Because they use a visual medium, they are very effective in reaching even the illiterate population. Documentaries provide factual information in an engaging format, helping to create social awareness and national pride. They serve as a historical record of India’s progress and are often screened in schools and public venues. The Films Division’s work ensures that mass media is used for the broader benefit of society."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 179,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the significance of the 10 incarnations of Vishnu in Dashavatara.",
            "answer": "The ten incarnations or 'Dashavatara' of Lord Vishnu form the core thematic content of the Dashavatara folk theatre. These include Matsya (fish), Koorma (tortoise), Varaha (boar), Narsimha (half-man half-lion), Wamana (dwarf), Parashurama, Rama, Krishna, Buddha, and Kalki. Each performance typically focuses on one or more of these stories, representing the triumph of good over evil. The use of these mythological stories connects the performance to the audience’s religious beliefs and cultural heritage. It allows the theatre to serve as a medium for religious education while providing entertainment. The colorful masks and dramatic enactments of these divine incarnations are a hallmark of this traditional coastal art form."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 180,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Describe the evolution of 'Gana' and 'Gavalan' in a Tamasha show.",
            "answer": "A traditional Tamasha show follows a specific sequence, starting with 'Gana' and 'Gavalan'. 'Gana' is an invocation song in praise of Lord Ganesha, sung to ensure the success of the performance. It is followed by 'Gavalan', which depicts the stories of Lord Krishna and the Gopis. The Gavalan part includes music, dance, and humorous dialogues between Krishna, Penya (the clown), and the Gopis. This introductory section sets the mood for the performance and establishes a connection with the audience. Historically, these elements represent the blending of devotional themes with folk entertainment, creating a comprehensive and highly engaging cultural experience."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 181,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the role of 'Shadange' in Indian classical painting.",
            "answer": "Ancient Indian scholars defined six main aspects or 'Shadange' for mastering the art of classical painting. These include Roopbheda (different shapes and forms), Pramana (proportionate depiction), Bhava (expressions), Lavanyayojana (aesthetics), Sadrushyata (resemblance to reality), and Varnikabhang (colour composition). These rules provide an established framework that an artist must follow to achieve excellence in classical art. Knowledge of Shadange requires prolonged training and a deep understanding of artistic theory. This disciplined approach ensured that Indian classical painting maintained high standards and a consistent aesthetic quality across different regions and historical periods."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 182,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain how the 'Samyukt Maharashtra' movement used folk arts.",
            "answer": "The Samyukt Maharashtra movement, aimed at creating a separate Marathi-speaking state, extensively used folk arts like Powada and Tamasha to mobilize public opinion. Shahirs (folk poets) composed Powadas that celebrated the history of Maharashtra and the valor of its people. These energetic performances were used to spread political messages and create a sense of regional unity. Tamasha troupes also incorporated themes related to the movement into their plays. By using traditional and familiar art forms, the leaders of the movement could effectively communicate with the masses and build a powerful grassroots movement. This historical example demonstrates the influence of entertainment as a tool for social and political change."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 183,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "What is 'Indo-Gothic' architecture and where can it be seen in India?",
            "answer": "Indo-Gothic architecture is a style that emerged during the British period, blending European Gothic features with Indian elements. It is characterized by pointed arches, ribbed vaults, and large windows. The British used this style for public buildings like churches, government offices, and railway stations to project their power. The finest example of this style is the Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj Railway Terminus in Mumbai, a UNESCO World Heritage site. Other examples include various high courts and university buildings in major cities. This architecture reflects the colonial history and the introduction of new engineering techniques in India during the 19th and early 20th centuries."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 184,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the 'antiquity' of Indian sculptural art using archaeological examples.",
            "answer": "The antiquity of Indian sculptural art is established by archaeological finds dating back over 5000 years. Harappan seals and statues show a high level of skill in making clay and metal figurines. Large-scale stone carving began in the Mauryan period with the Ashokan pillars and the Sanchi Stupa. The Gandhara and Mathura schools later introduced refined styles influenced by global contacts. The rock-cut caves at Ajanta and Verul and the bronze idols of the Chola period further testify to the continuous development of this art. These examples prove that sculpting is one of India's oldest and most sophisticated artistic traditions, evolving through various materials and religious themes."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 185,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "How did 'Sangeet Natak' influence the culture of Maharashtra?",
            "answer": "Sangeet Natak or Marathi musical theatre had a profound influence on the culture of Maharashtra during its golden age. It popularized classical khyal music among the masses, as the plays were filled with high-quality classical compositions. Legendary artists like Balgandharva became cultural icons, influencing everything from music to fashion. The plays addressed both mythological stories and social issues, serving as a medium for public education. The tradition fostered a deep appreciation for classical arts in the state and led to the establishment of several music and drama festivals. Today, Sangeet Natak is remembered as a prestigious part of Maharashtra’s heritage that successfully blended high art with popular entertainment."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 186,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the role of 'iconography' in identifying historical idols.",
            "answer": "Iconography is the specialized branch of knowledge concerned with making images of gods and goddesses according to set rules. It defines the specific attributes, proportions, and postures (asanas) for each deity. For historians, iconography is essential for identifying ancient idols and understanding their religious significance. By analyzing the features and symbols of an idol, researchers can determine the period it belongs to and the school of art that created it. The standardization of iconography during the Gupta period provided a consistent pattern for future artists. Thus, iconography serves as a vital tool for archaeological research and for the preservation of India’s religious and artistic history."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 187,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the contribution of 'Dadasaheb Phalke' as the father of Indian cinema.",
            "answer": "Dadasaheb Phalke is honored as the father of Indian cinema for his pioneering role in creating the first indigenous films. In 1913, he produced and directed India's first full-length movie, 'Raja Harischandra'. He took care of every aspect, from scriptwriting to technical processing. Phalke went on to create numerous silent movies based on mythological themes like 'Mohini-Bhasmasur'. His documentaries on pilgrim centers like Nashik and his innovative use of special effects laid the groundwork for the industry. By proving that filmmaking was possible and profitable in India, he inspired a generation of artists and technicians, leading to the birth of one of the world’s largest film industries."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 188,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "How does 'Applied Art' connect art with industrial and commercial traditions?",
            "answer": "Applied Art connects artistic creativity with utilitarian needs, making it highly relevant to industrial and commercial traditions. In fields like industry, advertising, and interior design, artists apply their skills to create products and spaces that are both functional and visually appealing. Training courses for applied arts include the study of industrial history and cultural traditions because every productive process has its own historical development. This historical context helps designers create products that resonate with the cultural identity of the audience. By combining beauty with utility, applied art professionalizes creativity and plays a crucial role in the modern economy by adding value to commercial products and services."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 189,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the significance of 'rock-cut caves' as a union of architecture and sculpture.",
            "answer": "Rock-cut caves, like those at Ajanta and Verul, represent a perfect union of architecture and sculptural art. Technically, the entire composition, including the carved columns, the idols on the walls, and the overall layout, is considered a monolithic sculpture. The architectural design of the caves, with their prayer halls (Chaityas) and living quarters (Viharas), demonstrates advanced engineering skills. Simultaneously, the intricate carvings and murals represent the peak of sculptural and painting traditions. These caves were created over centuries, reflecting the religious and social history of ancient India. Their declaration as World Heritage sites highlights their global importance as unique specimens of integrated artistic and structural skill."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 190,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the importance of 'Public Festivals' in providing accessible entertainment.",
            "answer": "Public festivals have historically been the most accessible sources of entertainment for all strata of society. In India, festivals like Ganesh Utsav or Holi have integrated folk theatre, music, and dance into their celebrations. These events provide a platform for folk artists to showcase their skills to a large audience. Public festivals also help keep traditional art forms alive by creating a regular demand for performances. In the modern period, festivals like the Savai Gandharva festival in Pune make classical music and dance accessible to the common people at a low cost. By bringing diverse arts into the public sphere, festivals foster communal harmony and ensure the continuity of cultural traditions across generations."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 191,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "How did the movie 'Sant Tukaram' achieve international recognition?",
            "answer": "The movie 'Sant Tukaram', produced by the Prabhat Film Company in 1936, was a landmark in Indian cinema. It was directed by V. Damle and S. Fattelal, and it featured Vishnupant Pagnis in the iconic role of the saint. The film was praised for its technical quality, realistic portrayal of rural life, and its spiritual depth. Its success was crowned when it received an award at an international film festival in Paris. This recognition proved that Indian cinema could achieve global standards and tell stories that resonated across different cultures. 'Sant Tukaram' remains a masterpiece of the talkie era, remembered for its simplicity, beautiful music, and historical importance as a global ambassador of Indian culture."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 192,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the role of 'Shahirs' in the folk tradition of Maharashtra.",
            "answer": "Shahirs are the folk poets and performers who are the heart of the Powada and Tamasha traditions in Maharashtra. They compose rhythmic ballads (Powadas) that celebrate heroism, social values, and historical events. A Shahir’s performance is characterized by high energy, vocal range, and the use of the 'Duff' (a musical instrument). Historically, Shahirs like Adnyandas and Tulasidas documented the valor of Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj. During social movements, Shahirs acted as powerful communicators, using their art to educate and mobilize the public. The Shahir tradition represents the voice of the people, keeping oral history alive and inspiring the community through the artistic narration of great deeds and social struggles."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 193,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the 'educational' purpose of 'Bharud' and its impact on the masses.",
            "answer": "Bharud is a unique folk song form in Maharashtra that was specifically designed for an educational purpose by saints like Eknath. By using humor, metaphors, and rhythmic music, Bharud delivers spiritual and ethical lessons in a way that is easily understood by the masses. The use of everyday social scenarios and characters makes the message relatable. The humorous nature of the performance ensures that even complex philosophical ideas don't become boring. This approach made Bharud an effective tool for social reform and moral education during the Bhakti movement. Even today, Bharuds are performed during religious gatherings, continuing to educate and entertain people while preserving the humanitarian values of the Marathi saint tradition."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 194,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "How do 'historical serials' on television help in viewing historical wonders at home?",
            "answer": "Historical serials on television use modern audio-visual technology to bring ancient monuments, forts, and empires into the homes of common people. Through high-quality sets and visual effects, they reconstruct historical wonders that might be in ruins today. These shows enable audiences to visualize the life styles, architecture, and geography of the past without traveling. Serials like 'Bharat Ek Khoj' or 'Raja Shivchhatrapati' create a visual history that is much more engaging than dry textbooks. This visual presentation sparks interest in heritage conservation and cultural tourism. By making historical wonders watchable and entertaining, television serials play a significant role in public education and the preservation of collective national memory."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 195,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the significance of 'Annasaheb Kirloskar' in Marathi musical theatre.",
            "answer": "Annasaheb Kirloskar was a towering figure in the history of Marathi theatre, credited with pioneering the 'Sangeet Natak' or musical play tradition. In 1880, his play 'Sangeet Shakuntal' marked the beginning of a golden age for Marathi drama. Kirloskar introduced the use of classical music to tell a story on stage, creating a highly popular and refined form of entertainment. His work broke the tradition of mythological plays with spontaneous dialogues by introducing structured scripts and elaborate music. He founded the Kirloskar Natak Mandali, which trained legendary artists like Balgandharva. Kirloskar’s contribution transformed Marathi theatre into a sophisticated cultural institution that successfully blended literature, classical music, and performance."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 196,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the 'professional' standards set by the Prabhat Film Company.",
            "answer": "The Prabhat Film Company set high professional and technical standards for the early Indian film industry. It invested in advanced equipment and nurturing specialized talent in acting, direction, and cinematography. The company was known for its meticulous research for historical and social themes, ensuring authenticity in costumes and sets. Their films, like 'Ramshastri' and 'Sant Tukaram', were admired for their high production value and artistic depth. Prabhat established a structured studio system that professionalized filmmaking in India. By focusing on quality and social relevance, the company influenced the future direction of both Marathi and Hindi cinema, proving that Indian movies could compete with global productions in both technique and storytelling."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 197,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "How does 'Knowledge of Language' assist in writing movie dialogues for historical themes?",
            "answer": "Knowledge of the specific language and dialects spoken in a concerned historical period is essential for writing authentic movie dialogues. Language evolves over time, and using modern slang in a historical setting can break the audience’s immersion and credibility. Writers must research the vocabulary, tone, and lingual expressions used by people during that era. For example, dialogues for a movie on the Peshwa period must reflect the Marathi of the 18th century. This linguistic accuracy helps in portraying characters realistically and reflects the cultural atmosphere of the time. Historians and language experts often collaborate with scriptwriters to ensure that the dialogues are historically grounded, making the entertainment both accurate and impactful."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 198,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the impact of 'Balgandharva' on the aesthetic and social life of Maharashtra.",
            "answer": "Narayanrao Rajahamsa, popularly known as Balgandharva, was a legendary figure who had a massive impact on the aesthetic and social life of Maharashtra. As a lead actor in musical plays, his portrayals of female characters were so graceful and realistic that they influenced women's fashion and style of the time. His singing popularized classical music and his performances brought thousands to the theaters. Balgandharva’s dedication to his art and his immense popularity made him a symbol of the high standards of Marathi musical theatre. He helped make the stage a respected professional field and his legacy continues to inspire artists and musicians, while his songs remain an integral part of Maharashtra’s cultural identity."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 199,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Explain the significance of the play 'Sharada' as a social commentary.",
            "answer": "The musical play 'Sharada', written by Govind Ballal Deval, is a landmark in Marathi theatre for its bold social commentary. It uses humor and satire to critique the evil practice of marrying young girls to elderly men for money. The character of 'Kanchanbhat' represents the greed and social decay of the time. By presenting a serious social issue in an entertaining musical format, Deval successfully created public awareness and supported the social reform movements of the late 19th century. 'Sharada' proved that theatre could be a powerful tool for social change, and its focus on women’s rights and social justice makes it a historically significant work that moved beyond mere entertainment to become a medium of reform."
        },
        {
            "question_id": 200,
            "question_type": "LONG",
            "question": "Discuss the role of 'hobbies and games' in personality development.",
            "answer": "Hobbies and games are essential forms of active entertainment that play a significant role in personality development. Engaging in a hobby, like practicing handicrafts or reading, provides mental stimulation and a sense of creative accomplishment. Participating in sports and games helps in physical growth and teaches important values like teamwork, discipline, and perseverance. These activities help individuals manage stress and keep their minds lively and fresh. By pursuing varied interests, people can develop diverse skills and a well-rounded personality. In India, many traditional festivals and community games have historically served this purpose, emphasizing that entertainment is not just for passing time but is vital for the holistic growth of an individual."
        }
    ]
}